<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" ?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="homepage.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!-- Written by Harold Boley -->

<homepage>

  <title>RuleML Homepage</title>

  <opening>
    <center>
      <a href="http://www.ruleml.org"><img src="http://www.ruleml.org/images/RuleMLlogo2005.jpg" border="none" alt="RuleML"/></a>

<!-- 
      <big>
        <box bgcolor="#CCCCFF"><code><![CDATA[

->]]></code></box>
        <box bgcolor="#FFCCCC">R u l e M L</box>
        <box bgcolor="#CCCCFF"><code><![CDATA[

<-]]></code></box>
      </big>
-->

      <br/>
<h1>The Rule Markup Initiative</h1>
    </center>

<br/>

<p>
The RuleML Initiative is an international non-profit organization covering all aspects of Web rules and their interoperation, with a <a href="#Structure">Structure</a> and Technical Groups that center on
RuleML specification, tool, and application development. Around RuleML, an open network of individuals and groups from both industry and academia has emerged,
having a shared interest in modern rule topics, including the interoperation of Semantic Web rules.
The RuleML Initiative has been collaborating with OASIS on <a href="http://www.legalxml.org/">Legal XML</a>, <a href="http://policy.ruleml.org/">Policy RuleML</a>, and related efforts since 2004.
The Initiative has further been interacting with the developers of ISO Common Logic (<a href="http://cl.tamu.edu/">CL</a>), which became an International Standard, First edition, in October 2007.
RuleML is also a member of OMG, contributing to its Semantics of Business Vocabulary and Business Rules (<a href="http://www.omg.org/spec/SBVR/">SBVR</a>),
which went into Version 1.0 in January 2008, and to its Production Rule Representation (<a href="http://www.omg.org/spec/PRR/">PRR</a>), which went into Version 1.0 in December 2009.
Moreover, participants of the RuleML Initiative have supported the development of the W3C Rule Interchange Format (<a href="http://www.w3.org/2005/rules/wiki/RIF_Working_Group">RIF</a>),
which attained Recommendation status in June 2010.
The annual <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/RuleML_Symposium">RuleML Symposium</a>
has taken the lead in bringing together delegates from industry and academia who share this interest focus in Web rules.
</p>
<p>
RuleML (Rule Markup Language) is a unifying family of XML-serialized rule languages spanning across all industrially relevant kinds of Web rules.
It accommodates and extends other recent rule languages, building interoperation bridges between them.
The <a href="#Specification">Specification</a> of RuleML is currently being developed from <a href="/0.91/">Version 0.91</a> to <a href="/1.0/">Version 1.0</a>.
</p>

  </opening>

<mission> <!-- rename to resources in .xslt and .xml -->
<header>Resources</header>
<p>
<b>Mission Statement:</b>
<p>
The goal of the Rule Markup Initiative is to develop RuleML as the
canonical Web language for rules using XML markup, formal semantics,
and efficient implementations.
</p>
<p>
RuleML covers the entire rule spectrum,
from derivation rules to transformation rules to
reaction rules. RuleML can thus specify queries and inferences in Web
ontologies, mappings between Web ontologies, and dynamic Web behaviors
of workflows, services, and agents.
</p>
<br/>
<b>Mission Approach:</b>
<p>
Rather than focusing on academic research prototypes, RuleML is about rule
interoperation between industry standards (such as JSR 94, SQL'99, OCL,
BPMI, WSFL, XLang, XQuery, RQL, OWL, DAML-S, and ISO Prolog) as well as
established systems (CLIPS, Jess, ILOG JRules, Blaze Advisor, Versata,
MQWorkFlow, BizTalk, Savvion, etc.).
</p>
<p>
The Initiative develops a modular RuleML specification and transformations 
from and to other rule standards/systems. Moreover, it coordinates the
development of tools to elicit, maintain, and execute RuleML rules.
It also collects use cases, e.g. on business rules and reactive services.
</p>
<br/>
<b>Tutorial:</b>
<p>
The <a href="http://www.ruleml.org/papers/tutorial-ruleml.html">RuleML Tutorial</a>
has its current focus on the kernel Datalog sublanguage.
</p>
<br/>

<b>Lists/Groups:</b>
<itemize>
<item>
  <a href="http://mail.ruleml.org/pipermail/ruleml-all/2003-November/000000.html">Subscribe</a> to our main mailing list:
  <a href="http://mail.ruleml.org/pipermail/ruleml-all/">ruleml-all</a>.
</item>
<item>
  Get up to date with the Fuzzy RuleML TG mailing list:
  <a href="http://mail.ruleml.org/pipermail/fuzzy-tg/">fuzzy-tg</a>.
</item>
<item>
  Peek into the Reaction Rules TG mailing list:
  <a href="http://mail.ruleml.org/pipermail/reaction-tg/">reaction-tg</a>.
</item>
<item>
  <a href="http://mail.jdrew.org/pipermail/jdrew-all/2005-June/000000.html">Consider</a> to join the engine mailing list:
  <a href="http://mail.jdrew.org/pipermail/jdrew-all/">jdrew-all</a>.
</item>
<item>
  Discuss Web rule-based agents on the Rule Responder TG mailing list:
  <a href="http://tech.groups.yahoo.com/group/Rule_Responder/">responder-tg</a>.
</item>
<item>
  Join the LinkedIn RuleML group or some of its subgoups:
  <a href="http://www.google.ca/search?q=LinkedIn+RuleML+group">LinkedIn RuleML group</a>.
</item>
</itemize>
</p>

<br/>
<b>Challenge Demos:</b>
<p>
The page for <b><a href="http://ruleml-challenge.cs.nccu.edu.tw/?q=submitform">RuleML Challenge Demos</a></b>
has been created by the research group of
<a href="http://www.cs.nccu.edu.tw/~jong/">Yuh-Jong Hu</a> from the
<a href="http://www.cs.nccu.edu.tw/">Department of Computer Science</a> at the
National Chengchi University (<a href="http://www.nccu.edu.tw/">NCCU</a>), Taipei, Taiwan, where it is being maintained by Jack.
</p>
</mission>

<news>
<header>News-Events</header>
<itemize>
  <item>The <a href="http://www.ruleml.org/inews.html">RuleML News-Events Archive</a> shows all previous news.
  </item>

  <item>Call for Presentations/Participation: <b>Special Rules Track at <a href="http://semtech2010.semanticuniverse.com/">SemTech 2010</a>, co-organized by RuleML</b>.
  For schedule and registration see: <a href="http://semtech2010.semanticuniverse.com/rules">Semantic Rules</a>
  </item>
  <item><b>Press Release</b>, Fredericton, Canada, Thessaloniki, Greece, April 23, 2010:
  <a href="http://ruleml.org/press/EmeraldRuleMLResponderPressRelease-2010-04-23.pdf">RuleML and Aristotle University Collaborate on Rule-Based Multi-Agent System Emerald RuleML Responder</a> 
  </item>
  <item>2010-06-22: With <a href="http://www.w3.org/2005/rules/wiki/RIF_FAQ#What_is_the_relationship_between_RuleML_and_RIF.3F">input from RuleML</a>,
  the <a href="http://www.w3.org/2005/rules/wiki/RIF_Working_Group">W3C RIF Working Group</a> published
  <a href="http://www.w3.org/News/2010#entry-8839">six recommendations and five related documents</a>.
  See also <a href="#RIF">RIF RuleML</a> developments.
  </item>
  <item>Recent <a href="http://responder.ruleml.org/">Rule Responder</a> instantiations include
    <itemize>
    <item>
    <a href="http://ruleml.org/SymposiumPlanner">SymposiumPlanner</a>-2009/2010,
    </item>
    <item>
    <a href="http://ruleml.org/WellnessRules">WellnessRules</a>/<a href="http://ruleml.org/WellnessRules2">WellnessRules2</a>, and
    </item>
    <item>
    <a href="http://ruleml.org/PatientSupporter">PatientSupporter</a>,
    </item>
  </itemize>
  using RuleML for (Prolog-N3) interchange.
  </item>
  <item><b>The 4th International Web Rule Symposium: Research Based and Industry Focused</b>
  (<a href="http://2010.ruleml.org" title="RuleML-2010">RuleML-2010</a>) will take place
  in Washington, DC, USA, October 21-23, 2010, co-located with the Business Rules Forum Conference 2010
  (<a href="http://www.businessrulesforum.com" title="BR Forum">BR Forum</a>).
  RuleML-2010 is the premier industry-focused event to discuss and exchange new ideas,
  practical developments and experiences on all topics related to the engineering,
  management, integration, interoperation and interchange of rules in open
  distributed environments such as the Web or Enterprise Systems. RuleML-2010 will enable delegates
  to better understand Web/Enterprise rules and rule-based event processing technologies
  and their potential, and how to exploit these technologies in their own organizations.
  The proceedings will <a href="http://www.springer.com/computer/information+systems+and+applications/book/978-3-642-04984-2">again</a>
  be published as Springer LNCS.
  <a href="http://logic.stanford.edu/people/genesereth/">Michael Genesereth</a> and
  <a href="http://www.drrw.net/">David Webber</a>
  will give keynotes.
  Go to <a href="http://2010.ruleml.org/call-for-papers.html">RuleML-2010 Call for Papers</a>
  and then to <a href="http://www.csw.inf.fu-berlin.de/ruleml2010/ruleml-2010-challenge.html">RuleML-2010 Challenge</a>:
  <itemize>
    <item>
    Extended Abstract submission deadline: June 6, 2010
    </item>
    <item>
    Extended Paper Submission deadline: June 11, 2010
    </item>
    <item>
    Challenge Paper Submission deadline (EXTENDED): Aug. 27, 2010
    </item>
  </itemize>
  </item>
  <item>2010-10-21: <a href="http://2010.ruleml.org" title="RuleML-2010">RuleML-2010</a> presentations for the Washington DC Semantic Web Meetup Group (<a href="http://www.meetup.com/semweb-31/calendar/14349685/">Lotico Washington Semantic Web</a>)
  start with brief Introduction slides (<a href="http://files.meetup.com/987383/RuleML-SemWeb-Meetup-2010.pptx">RuleML - Where Web Rule Research Meets Industry</a>)
  </item>
  <item>2010-12-28: The well-known Wine Ontology is made available as a sizeable RuleML Use Case in Web rule conversion, upgrading, and normalization (<a href="http://ruleml.org/usecases/wineonto/">WineOnto</a>)
  </item>
  <item>
2011-01-18: <a href="http://responder.ruleml.org/">Rule Responder</a> and <a href="http://lpis.csd.auth.gr/systems/emerald/">EMERALD</a> are multi-agent systems assisting user communities based on Semantic Web and multi-agent standards.
The <a href="http://ruleml.org/press/EmeraldRuleMLResponderPressRelease-2010-04-23.pdf">Collaboration between RuleML and Aristotle University</a> made these multi-agent systems
interoperable in order to automate collaboration across communities using a declarative, knowledge-based approach.
Bidirectional RuleML gateways between EMERALD and Rule Responder were built, which could also be adapted for other interoperation needs.
Multi-step interaction scenarios among agents based on the <a href="http://ruleml.org/SymposiumPlanner/">SymposiumPlanner</a> use case have been deployed through the <a href="http://ruleml.org/RuleML-2010/RuleResponder/RuleResponder.htm">RuleML-2010 Symposium Q&amp;A web page</a>.
Details are found on the <a href="http://lpis.csd.auth.gr/systems/EMERALDRR/">EMERALD Rule Responder website</a>.
  </item>
<item><b>Call for Papers for the 5th International Symposium on Rules: Research Based, Industry Focused</b> (<a href="http://2011.ruleml.org" title="RuleML-2011">RuleML-2011</a>).
In 2011, two instalments of the RuleML Symposium will take place.
The first one will be held in conjunction with the
International Joint Conference on Artificial Intelligence (<a href="http://ijcai-11.iiia.csic.es/">IJCAI 2011</a>)
in Barcelona, Spain, July 16th-22th, 2011.
The second one will be co-located with the Business Rules
Forum 2011 (<a href="http://www.businessrulesforum.com/">BRF 2011</a>) to be held in Fort Lauderdale, Florida, USA, November 3rd-5th, 2011. The
<a href="http://2011.ruleml.org/america/">RuleML-2011@BRF</a> instalment will include the <a href="http://2011.ruleml.org/america/?page_id=126">RuleML Challenge Award</a>, which this year will be dedicated to Rules and Ontologies.
For RuleML-2011@IJCAI a selection of best papers will be presented during a
joint session with IJCAI, and the authors of these papers will be invited to
submit a revised paper for inclusion into the IJCAI proceedings.
</item>
  <item>
    2011-03-17:
    <a href="http://www.alt2is.com">Athan Services</a>
     and RuleML have started a project
    on re-engineering and improving the RuleML XSDs in
    <a href="http://relaxng.org/">Relax NG</a>.
    The first result of this project is a version of RuleML 0.91 in Relax NG,
    which implements bindatalog in the normal form.
    The modular design of the Relax NG schema will allow greater flexibility
    in customizing language features, increased ease of development,
    testing, and documentation.
    The design also prepares the way for the second phase
    of the project, the alignment of a subset of RuleML with
    <a href="http://common-logic.org/">Common Logic.</a>  
    Items currently available for alpha-testing from the RuleML website
    include the
    <a href="http://ruleml.org/0.91/relaxng">Relax NG schema</a>,
    <a href="http://code.google.com/p/jing-trang/">Trang</a>-generated <a href="http://ruleml.org/0.91/trang">XSD schema</a>, and
    <a href="http://www.oxygenxml.com/">oXygen</a>-generated
    <a href="http://ruleml.org/0.91/docng/bindatalog_normal/">documentation</a>.
    The principles of this approach are discussed on the <a href ="http://wiki.ruleml.org/index.php/Relax_NG">Relax NG - RuleML Wiki</a> Page.
  </item>
</itemize>
</news>

<section label="Initiative">
<header>The Initiative</header>
<p>
The <a href="#Participants-Logos">participants</a> of the RuleML Initiative
constitute an open network of
individuals and groups from both industry and academia. We are not
commencing from zero but have done some work related to rule markup or have
actually proposed some specific tag set for rules.
Our main objective is to provide a basis for an integrated rule-markup approach
that will be beneficial to all involved and to the rule community
at large. This shall be achieved by having all participants
collaborate in establishing translations between existing tag sets and
in converging on a shared rule-markup vocabulary.
This RuleML kernel language can
serve as a specification for immediate rule interchange and can be gradually
extended - possibly together with <a href="#Related">related initiatives</a> -
towards a proposal that could be submitted to the
<a href="http://www.w3.org/">W3C</a>.
</p>
</section>

<section label="Uses">
<header>Uses</header>
<box bgcolor="#CCCCFF">
<a name="Example-English"/>
If you want to review rule principles,
(then) you may look at
<a href="http://www.cs.nott.ac.uk/~sxp/ES3/index.htm">Rule-Based Expert Systems</a>. (<a href="insteps.html#Example-RuleML">BTW, this is itself a simple rule</a>.)
If you want to review XML principles,
you may go to the beginning of
<a href="http://www.dfki.uni-kl.de/km/knowmark/">Knowledge Markup Techniques</a>.
</box>

<p>
Rules are being used for many interconnected purposes,
capturing regularities in
application domains such as the following:
<itemize>
  <item>Engineering: Diagnosis rules (also model-based approaches appreciate
and combine with rules, as described by Adnan Darwiche in
<a href="http://www.cs.ucla.edu/~darwiche/realize.ps">Model-based diagnosis under real-world constraints</a>,
AI Magazine, Summer 2000)
  </item>
  <item>Commerce: Business rules (including XML versions such as the
Business Rules Markup Language
(<a href="http://www.oasis-open.org/cover/brml.html">BRML</a>) of IBM's
<a href="http://www.research.ibm.com/rules/home.html">Business Rules for Electronic Commerce</a>
project)
  </item>
  <item>Law: Legal reasoning (Robert Kowalski and Marek Sergot have been
formalizing legal rules in an <a href="http://www-lp.doc.ic.ac.uk/ProjectPages/legal.html">Imperial College group</a>)
  </item>
  <item>Internet: Access authentication
(Tim Berners-Lee proposed registration engines that use authentication rules
<a href="http://www.w3.org/DesignIssues/Inconsistent.html">such as the following</a>:
Any person who was some time in the last 2 months an employee
of an organization which was some time in the last 2 months a
W3C member may register.)
  </item>
</itemize>

Rather than reinventing rule principles and markups in each such community,
the idea of RuleML is to 'package' the rule aspect of these domains and
and make it available as an
<a href="http://www.w3.org/TR/REC-xml-names/">(XML) namespace</a>,
<tt>.../RuleML</tt>, which can be mixed with
a namespace for
natural-language (<a href="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/">XHTML</a>) texts
and possible domain-specific namespaces
(much like <a href="http://www.w3.org/Math/">MathML</a> is mixed into
such domain texts).
</p>
</section>

<section>
<header>Scope</header>
<p>
Rules can be stated (1) in natural language, (2) in some formal notation,
or (3) in a combination of both. Being in the third, 'semiformal' category,
the RuleML Initiative is working towards an XML-based markup language that
permits Web-based rule storage, interchange, retrieval, and firing/application.
</p>
<a name="Related"/>
<p>
Markup standards and initiatives related to RuleML include:
<itemize>
  <item>Mathematical Markup Language
(<a href="http://www.w3.org/Math/">MathML</a>):
However, MathML's <i>Content Markup</i> is better suited for defining functions
rather than relations or general rules
  </item>
  <item>DARPA Agent Markup Language (<a href="http://www.daml.org/">DAML</a>):
While the contributing
<a href="http://www.cs.umd.edu/projects/plus/SHOE/">SHOE project</a>
has permitted Horn rules and a DAML-RULES is planned, the current
<a href="http://www.daml.org/language/">DAML+OIL</a> (March 2001)
does not yet include a specification of explicit inference rules
  </item>
  <item>Predictive Model Markup Language
(<a href="http://www.dmg.org/html/pmml_v1_1.html">PMML</a>):
With this XML-based language one can define and share various models
for data-mining results, including
<a href="http://www.dmg.org/html/assocrules.html">association rules</a>
  </item>
  <item>Attribute Grammars in XML (<a href="http://www.dfki.uni-kl.de/~boley/xmlag/attgramm/sld001.htm">AG-markup</a>):
For AG's semantic rules, there are various possible XML markups that are
similar to Horn-rule markup
  </item>
  <item>Extensible Stylesheet Language Transformations
(<a href="http://www.w3.org/TR/xslt">XSLT</a>):
This is a restricted term-rewriting system of rules, written in XML,
for transforming XML documents into other XML documents
  </item>
</itemize>
</p>
</section>


<section label="Participants-Logos">
<header>Participants' Logos</header>
<p>
The RuleML Initiative consists of <a href="http://www.dfki.de/~urban/ruleml/inlogos.html">the participants represented here by their logos</a>.
</p>
</section>


<section label="Participants-Systems">
<header>Participants' Systems (Updated: 2008-07-22)</header>
<box bgcolor="#CCCCFF">
<box bgcolor="#FFCCCC">
Besides on the <a href="#Related">related work</a>, the RuleML Initiative is based on
the following systems of the participants listed in parentheses:

    <enumerate>
      <item><a href="http://www.cs.mu.oz.au/agentlab/">Agent Frameworks</a>
            (<a href="http://www.cs.mu.oz.au/~leon/">Leon Sterling</a>,
             <a href="http://www.cs.mu.oz.au/">Department of Computer Science and Software Engineering, University of Melbourne</a>, Australia)
      </item>
      <item><a href="http://www.haifa.il.ibm.com/projects/software/amit/">AMIT/ADI</a>
            (<a href="http://www.research.ibm.com/people/a/adi/">Asaf Adi</a>,
             <a href="mailto:sommer@il.ibm.com">Ziva Sommer</a>,
             <a href="http://www.haifa.il.ibm.com/">IBM Research Lab in Haifa</a>, Israel)
      </item>
      <item><a href="http://tmitwww.tm.tue.nl/staff/gwagner/AORML/">AORML</a>
            (<a href="http://tmitwww.tm.tue.nl/staff/gwagner/">Gerd Wagner</a>,
             <a href="http://tmitwww.tm.tue.nl/index-e.html">Faculty of Technology Management, I &amp; T, Eindhoven University of Technology</a>, The Netherlands)
      </item>
      <item><a href="http://www.mindbox.com/solutions/products.shtml">ARTEnterprise</a>
            (<a href="mailto:samir.rohatgi@mindbox.com">Samir Rohatgi</a>,
             <a href="mailto:brian.sauk@mindbox.com">Brian Sauk</a>,
             <a href="http://www.mindbox.com">MindBox Inc.</a>, USA)
      </item>
      <item><a href="http://www.kr.tuwien.ac.at/staff/roman/aspruleml/">ASP RuleML</a>
            (<a href="http://www.kr.tuwien.ac.at/staff/roman/">Roman Schindlauer</a>,
             <a href="http://www.kr.tuwien.ac.at/staff/eiter/eiter.html">Thomas Eiter</a>,
	     Vienna University of Technology;
             <a href="http://www.mat.unical.it/~ianni/">Giovambattista Ianni</a>,
	     Universita' della Calabria;
	     Austria, Italy)
      </item>     
      <item><a href="http://www.smartbot-technologies.de/botform.html">BotForm&amp;trade</a>
            (<a href="mailto:sven.seelig@smartbot-technologies.de">Sven Seelig</a>,
             <a href="mailto:sml@smartbot-technologies.de">Sonja Muller Landmann</a>,
             <a href="http://www.smartbot-technologies.de">Smart Bot Technologies</a>, Germany)
      </item>
      <item><a href="http://ebusiness.mit.edu/bgrosof/paps/fipa-grosof-07-00-distrib.ps">BRML/DAML-RULES</a>
            (<a href="http://ebusiness.mit.edu/bgrosof/">Benjamin Grosof</a>,
             <a href="http://mitsloan.mit.edu">MIT Sloan School of Management</a>, USA)
      </item>
      <item><a href="http://www.pi4soa.org">CDL</a>
            (<a href="mailto:steve@pi4tech.com">Steve Ross-Talbot</a>,
             <a href="http://www.pi4tech.com/">Pi4 Technologies</a>;
             UK)
      </item>
      <item><a href="http://www.research.ibm.com/rules">CommonRules</a>
            (<a href="mailto:hychan@us.ibm.com">Hoi Chan</a>,
             <a href="http://www.research.ibm.com">IBM T.J. Watson Research</a>, USA)
      </item>
      <item><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-bremen.de/~ga/research/ruleml.html">Deimos&amp;Phobos</a>
            (<a href="http://www.ics.forth.gr/~antoniou/">Grigoris Antoniou</a>,
             <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-bremen.de/">Fachbereich Mathematik &amp; Informatik, Universität Bremen</a>, Germany)
      </item>
      <item><a href="http://lpis.csd.auth.gr/systems/dr-device.html">DR-DEVICE</a>
            (<a href="http://www.csd.auth.gr/~nick">Nick Bassiliades</a>,
             <a href="http://www.csd.auth.gr/~lpis">Logic Programming and Intelligent Systems (LPIS) Group</a>,
             <a href="http://www.csd.auth.gr/index.en.php">Dept. of Informatics</a>,
             <a href="http://www.auth.gr">Aristotle University of Thessaloniki</a>, Greece;
	     <a href="http://www.ics.forth.gr/~antoniou">Grigoris Antoniou</a>,
             <a href="http://www.ics.forth.gr/isl/">Information Systems Laboratory</a>,
             <a href="http://www.ics.forth.gr/">Institute of Computer Science</a>,
             <a href="http://www.forth.gr">FORTH</a>, Heraklion, Crete, Greece)
      </item>
      <item><a href="http://www.sybase.com/detail?id=1012526">EAI Rules engine</a>
            (<a href="mailto:rwhalen@sybase.com">Ruth Whalen</a>, <a href="mailto:Darren.Damato@New-Era-of-Networks.com">Darren D'Amato</a>,
             <a href="http://www.sybase.com/">Sybase Database Management Systems</a>, <a href="http://www.sybase.com/neweraofnetworks">New Era Of Networks, Inc.</a>, USA)
      </item>
      <item><a href="http://www.agfa.com/w3c/euler/">Euler</a>
            (<a href="http://www.agfa.com/w3c/jdroo/">Jos De Roo</a>,
             <a href="http://www.agfa.com/">AGFA</a>, Belgium)
      </item>
      <item><a href="http://www.dsic.upv.es/~jorallo/flip/">FLIP</a>
            (<a href="http://www.dsic.upv.es/~jorallo/">Jose Hernandez-Orallo</a>,
             <a href="http://www.dsic.upv.es/">DSIC</a>, <a href="http://www.upv.es/">Politechnical University of Valencia</a>, Spain)
      </item>
      <item>Java Forward-Chaining Engines Integration
            (<a href="mailto:ebonnet_NO_SPAM_EMAIL@genigraph.fr">Emmanuel Bonnet</a>,
             <a href="mailto:gmolines@optechsoftware.com">Guilhem Molines</a>,
             <a href="mailto:onicolas_NO_SPAM_EMAIL@genigraph.fr">Olivier Nicolas</a>,
             <a href="http://www.genigraph.fr">Genigraph/OpTech Software</a>, France, USA)
      </item>
      <item><a href="http://flora.sourceforge.net">Flora-2</a>
            (<a href="http://www.cs.sunysb.edu/~kifer">Michael Kifer</a>,
             <a href="http://www.cs.sunysb.edu/~guizyang">Guizhen Yang</a>,
             <a href="http://www.cs.sunysb.edu">Department of Computer Science</a>
             <a href="http://www.stonybrook.edu">State University of New York at Stony Brook</a>, USA)
      </item>
      <item><a href="http://www.iit.nrc.ca/www/E_Business/Research.html">jDREW</a>
            (<a href="http://www.cs.unb.ca/~bspencer">Bruce Spencer</a>,
             <a href="http://www.cs.unb.ca">Faculty of Computer Science</a>,
             <a href="http://www.unb.ca">University of New Brunswick</a> and
             <a href="http://www.iit.nrc.ca/">Institute for Information Technology</a>,
             <a href="http://www.nrc.ca/">National Research Council of Canada</a>, Canada)
      </item>
      <item><a href="http://herzberg.ca.sandia.gov/jess/">Jess</a>
            (<a href="http://herzberg.ca.sandia.gov">Ernest Friedman-Hill</a>,
             <a href="http://www.sandia.gov/">Distributed Systems Research, Sandia National Labs</a>, USA)
      </item>
      <item>KNOW: Knowledge Norm Of Webmind
            (<a href="mailto:Pei.Wang@temple.edu">Pei Wang</a>,
             <a href="http://www.webmind.com/">Webmind Inc.</a>, USA)
      </item>
      <item><a href="http://lispminer.vse.cz">LispMiner</a>
            (<a href="http://nb.vse.cz/~svatek/welcom_e.htm">Vojtech Svatek</a>,
             <a href="mailto:rauch@vse.cz">Jan Rauch</a>,
             <a href="mailto:xlinv05@vse.cz">Vaclav Lin</a>,
             <a href="http://nb1.vse.cz/~svatek/ke_group.htm">Knowledge Engineering Group</a>,
             <a href="http://kizi2.vse.cz">Department of Information and Knowledge Engineering (DIKE)</a>,
             <a href="http://www.vse.cz">University of Economics, Prague</a>, Czech Republic)
      </item>
      <item><a href="http://machine-knows.etri.re.kr/bossam/docs/logicml.html">LogicML</a>/<a href="http://machine-knows.etri.re.kr/bossam">Bossam Rule Engine</a>
            (<a href="mailto:minsu@etri.re.kr">Minsu Jang</a>,
             <a href="mailto:jcsohn@etri.re.kr">Joochan Sohn</a>,
             <a href="http://www.etri.re.kr/e_etri/">ETRI</a>, Korea)
      </item>
      <item><a href="http://www.mandarax.org/">Mandarax</a>
            (<a href="mailto:jens.dietrich@unforgettable.com">Jens Dietrich</a>,
             Department of Computer Science, <a href="http://www.polytechnic.edu.na/">Polytechnic of Namibia</a>, Namibia)
      </item>
      <item><a href="http://galeb.etf.bg.ac.yu/~vm/papers/r7inen3.lo.pdf">Obelix</a>
            (<a href="http://galeb.etf.bg.ac.yu/~vm">Veljko Milutinovic</a>,
             <a href="mailto:sasa@galeb.etf.bg.ac.yu">Sasa Mitrovic</a>,
             <a href="http://www.etf.bg.ac.yu/?lang=en">Faculty of Electrical Engineering</a>,
             <a href="http://www.beograd.org.yu/english/zivot/obrnauka/univerz/">University of Belgrade</a>,
             Serbia and Montenegro)
      </item>
      <item><a href="http://kmi.open.ac.uk/projects/ocml/">OCML</a>
            (<a href="http://kmi.open.ac.uk/people/motta/">Enrico Motta</a>,
             <a href="http://kmi.open.ac.uk/people/domingue/">John Domingue</a>,
             <a href="http://kmi.open.ac.uk/home-t.cfm">Knowledge Media Institute</a>,
             <a href="http://www.open.ac.uk/">The Open University</a>,
             UK)
      </item>
      <item><a href="http://www.i-u.de/schools/eberhart/ontojava/">OntoJava</a>
            (<a href="http://www.aifb.uni-karlsruhe.de/WBS/aeb/">Andreas Eberhart</a>,
             <a href="http://www.i-u.de/">International University in Germany</a>, Germany)
      </item>
      <item><a href="http://www.inf.fu-berlin.de/inst/ag-nbi/research/owltrans/">OWLTrans</a>
            (<a href="http://www.is.pku.edu.cn/~mayyam/">Jing Mei</a>,
             <a href="http://www.inf.fu-berlin.de/inst/ag-nbi/">Networked Information Systems</a>,
	     <a href="http://www.fu-berlin.de/">Freie Universität Berlin</a>, Germany)
      </item>
      <item><a href="http://cs-www.cs.yale.edu/homes/dvm/">PDDL: Planning Domain Definition Language</a>
            (<a href="http://cs-www.cs.yale.edu/homes/dvm/">Drew V. McDermott</a>,
             <a href="http://www.cs.yale.edu/">Department of Computer Science, Yale University</a>, USA)
      </item>
      <item><a href="http://protege.stanford.edu">Protégé-2000</a>
            (<a href="http://smi-web.stanford.edu/people/musen/">Mark Musen</a>,
             <a href="http://smi-web.Stanford.EDU/">Stanford Medical Informatics</a>, USA)
      </item>
      <item><a href="http://www.prova.ws">Prova Language for Rule-based Java Scripting, Information Integration, and Agent Programming</a>
           (<a href="http://www.soi.city.ac.uk/~firmata">Alex Kozlenkov</a>,
             <a href="http://www.soi.city.ac.uk">School of Informatics</a>,
             <a href="http://www.city.ac.uk">City University, London</a>, UK)
      </item>
      <item>RBML: Rule Base Markup Language
            (<a href="http://www.geocities.com/Christopher.Roberts/">Chris Roberts</a>,
             <a href="http://www.sun.com/">Sun Microsystems</a>, USA)
      </item>
      <item><a href="http://ibis.in.tum.de/staff/paschke/rbsla/index.htm">RBSLA: Rule-based Service Level Agreements</a>
            (<a href="http://ibis.in.tum.de/staff/paschke/index.htm">Adrian Paschke</a>,
             <a href="http://ibis.in.tum.de/index.htm">Internet-based Information Systems (IBIS) </a>,
             <a href="http://www.in.tum.de/index_en.html">Department of Informatics, Technical University Munich</a>, Germany)
      </item>
      <item><a href="http://www.relfun.org/rfml/">RFML</a>
            (<a href="http://www.cs.unb.ca/~boley/">Harold Boley</a>,
             <a href="http://www.dfki.de/">DFKI</a>, Germany)
      </item>
      <item><a href="http://arabella.mcm.unisg.ch/SeCo/">SeCo</a>
            (<a href="http://www.netacademy.org/netacademy/register.nsf/mcm_staff/bschmid">Beat Schmid</a>,
             <a href="http://www.mcm.unisg.ch/">Institute for Media and Communications Management</a>,
             University of St. Gallen, Switzerland)
      </item>
      <item><a href="http://www.damlsmm.ri.cmu.edu">Semantic Matchmaker</a>
            (<a href="http://www-2.cs.cmu.edu/%7Esycara/">Katia Sycara</a>,
             <a href="http://www-2.cs.cmu.edu/~softagents/atlas/homepages/paolucci_massimo.html">Massimo Paolucci</a>,
             <a href="http://www-2.cs.cmu.edu/~softagents">The Intelligent Software Agents Lab</a>,
             <a href="http://www.ri.cmu.edu">The Robotics Institute</a>,
             <a href="http://www.cs.cmu.edu">School of Computer Science</a>,
             <a href="http://www.cmu.edu">Carnegie Mellon University</a>, USA)
      </item>
      <item><a href="http://www.dfki.uni-kl.de/frodo/triple/">TRIPLE</a>
            (<a href="http://www.stefandecker.org/">Stefan Decker</a>,
             <a href="http://www.deri.ie/">Digital Enterprise Research Institute</a>;
             <a href="http://www.dfki.uni-kl.de/~sintek/">Michael Sintek</a>,
             <a href="http://www.dfki.de/">DFKI</a>;
             Germany, Ireland)
      </item>
      <item><a href="http://www.ida.liu.se/~pawpi/research.html">Type-Based Diagnoser</a>
            (<a href="http://www.ida.liu.se/~janma/">Jan Maluszynski</a>,
             <a href="http://www.ida.liu.se/sweb/">Swedish Semantic Web Initiative</a>,
             <a href="http://www.ida.liu.se/index.en.shtml">Department of Computer and Information Science</a>,
             <a href="http://www.lith.liu.se/en/index.html">Linköping University</a>,
             Sweden)
      </item>
      <item><a href="http://home.comcast.net/~stabet/urml.html">URML</a>
            (<a href="mailto:david_ash99@yahoo.com">David Ash</a>,
             <a href="http://www.realtimeagentsinc.com">Real Time Agents Inc.</a>;
             <a href="mailto:prabhakar_bhogaraju@yahoo.com">Prabhakar Bhogaraju</a>,
             <a href="http://www.mindbox.com/">MindBox</a>;
             <a href="http://home.comcast.net/~stabet/">Said Tabet</a>,
             <a href="http://www.macgregor.com/">Macgregor Inc.</a>;
             USA)
      </item>
      <item>Versata Logic Suite for Transaction Logic
            (<a href="mailto:James_Liddle@Versata.com">James Liddle</a>,
             <a href="mailto:Kamran_Yousaf@Versata.com">Kamran Yousaf</a>,
             <a href="HTTP://WWW.Versata.com">Versata</a>;
             UK)
      </item>
      <item><a href="http://www.soi.city.ac.uk/~msch/cgi/viva/">Vivid Agents</a>/<a href="http://www.soi.city.ac.uk/~msch/revise/revise.html">Revise</a>
            (<a href="http://www.soi.city.ac.uk/~msch/">Michael Schroeder</a>,
             <a href="http://www.soi.city.ac.uk/">The School of Informatics</a>,
             <a href="http://www.city.ac.uk/">City University London</a>,
             UK)
      </item>
      <item>VPP
            (<a href="mailto:randerson@macgregor.ws">Rand Anderson</a>,
             <a href="http://www.macgregor.ws">Macgregor</a>, USA)
      </item>
      <item><a href="http://centria.di.fct.unl.pt/~cd/projectos/w4/index.htm">W4</a>
            (<a href="http://centria.di.fct.unl.pt/~cd">Carlos Viegas Damásio</a>,
             <a href="http://centria.di.fct.unl.pt/">CENTRIA (Centro de Inteligência Artificial da
Universidade Nova de Lisboa)</a>, Portugal)
      </item>
      <item><a href="http://www.xcerpt.org">Xcerpt</a>
            (<a href="http://www.pms.informatik.uni-muenchen.de/mitarbeiter/bry/">François Bry</a>,
             <a href="http://www.wastl.net/">Sebastian Schaffert</a>,
             <a href="http://www.pms.informatik.uni-muenchen.de/index-e.html">Teaching and Research Unit Programming and Modelling Language</a>,
             <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-muenchen.de/index-e.html">Institute of Computer Science, Ludwig-Maximilians-Universität München</a>, Germany)
      </item>
      <item><a href="http://kr.cs.ait.ac.th/xet/">XET</a>/<a href="http://kr.cs.ait.ac.th/XDD/">XDD</a>
            (<a href="mailto:vw@cs.ait.ac.th">Vilas Wuwongse</a>,
             <a href="mailto:ca@cs.ait.ac.th">Chutiporn Anutariya</a>,
             <a href="http://kr.cs.ait.ac.th/">Knowledge Representation Laboratory</a>,
             <a href="http://www.ait.ac.th/">Asian Institute of Technology</a>, Thailand)
      </item>
      <item><a href="http://xrml.kaist.ac.kr">XRML</a>
            (<a href="http://iis.kaist.ac.kr/~jklee/">Jae Kyu Lee</a>,
             <a href="http://icec.net/">ICEC</a>,
             <a href="http://iis.kaist.ac.kr/">KAIST</a>, Korea)
      </item>
    </enumerate>
</box>
</box>
<p>
2001-05-11:
"RuleML, the emerging standards effort on XML Rules knowledge
representation, continues to progress in its design -- and also in its
acceptance; notably, IBM this past month joined as participant and publicly
disclosed that it is prototyping support for RuleML.  Presentation
materials from two recent W3C meetings, and a new short overview conference
paper, are now available:  see <a href="http://ebusiness.mit.edu/bgrosof/#XMLRules">http://ebusiness.mit.edu/bgrosof/#XMLRules</a>."
(Also see: <a href="http://www.alphaworks.ibm.com/tech/commonrules">alphaWorks Posting</a>. Contact: <a href="mailto:hychan@us.ibm.com">Hoi Chan</a>.)
</p>
</section>


<section label="Steps">
<header>Initial Steps</header>
<p>
Some 
<a href="insteps.html">initial steps taken by the RuleML Initiative</a>
have been
to structure the area of rule markup,
to raise issues and identify tasks, and
to propose tentative rule tags/attributes.
</p>
</section>


<section label="Design">
<header>Design</header>
<p>
The 
<a href="indesign.html">current RuleML design</a>
shows the big picture of how we conceive and formalize rule markup;
this has been the basis of much of our more specific work.
</p>
</section>


<section label="Specification">
<header>Specification</header>

<p>
2001-01-31: A preliminary RuleML DTD has been released:
<a href="indtd.html">RuleML DTD Version 0.7</a>.
</p>
<p>
2001-07-11: A revised DTD version has been finalized:
<a href="indtd0.8.html">RuleML DTD Version 0.8</a>.
</p>
<p>
2001-09-25: A preliminary XML Schema for a Datalog subset of RuleML has been released:
<a href="inxsd0.8.html">RuleML Schema Version 0.8</a>.
</p>
<p>
2002-04-02: A query DTD version has been realized (cf. <a href="#Queries">Queries</a>):
<a href="indtd0.8.html">RuleML DTD Version 0.8</a>.
</p>
<p>
2004-01-28: A revised DTD/XSD version has been released:
<a href="0.85/">RuleML Version 0.85</a>.
</p>
<p>
2004-07-15: A stable XSD version has been released:
<a href="0.86/">RuleML Version 0.86</a>.
</p>
<p>
2004-08-12: A new XSD version has been released:
<a href="0.87/">RuleML Version 0.87</a>.
</p>
<p>
2004-11-02: A monolithic DTD version of FOL RuleML 0.9 has been released:
<a href="http://www.ruleml.org/fol/">FOL RuleML Version 0.9</a>.
</p>
<p>
2005-03-01: A new XSD version has been released: <a href="0.88/">RuleML Version 0.88</a>.
</p>
<p>
2005-05-27: A new XSD version has been released: <a href="0.89/">RuleML Version 0.89</a>.
</p>
<p>
2005-11-09: A new XSD version has been released: <a href="0.9/">RuleML Version 0.9</a>.
</p>
<p>
2006-08-24: A new XSD version has been released: <b><a href="0.91/">RuleML Version 0.91</a></b>.
</p>
<p>
2010-08-15: A preliminary new XSD version is being developed: <b><a href="1.0/">RuleML Version 1.0</a></b>.
</p>
</section>


<section label="Queries">
<header>Queries</header>

<p>
As in many deduction approaches, RuleML queries are regarded as headless implications,
symmetrically to regarding facts as bodiless
implications. They enumerate the bindings of all their free (existentially interpreted) variables.
</p>
<p>
Queries were added to RuleML 0.8 as a third top-level element of rulebases besides facts and imps
(since this extension is purely additive, all queriless RuleML 0.8 rulebases should still validate).
This gives us "for free" all refinements of RuleML's existing system of sublanguages via the _body
role of queries:
because of RuleML's DTD inheritance, additions were only required for
<a href="http://www.ruleml.org/dtd/0.8/ruleml-datalog.dtd">ruleml-datalog.dtd</a>
(<a href="http://www.ruleml.org/dtd/0.8/ruleml-datalog.dtd.txt">ruleml-datalog.dtd.txt</a>)
and
<a href="http://www.ruleml.org/dtd/0.8/ruleml-urcbindatagroundfact.dtd">urcbindatagroundfact.dtd</a>
(<a href="http://www.ruleml.org/dtd/0.8/ruleml-urcbindatagroundfact.dtd.txt">urcbindatagroundfact.dtd.txt</a>).
In particular,
<a href="http://www.ruleml.org/dtd/0.8/ruleml-datalog.dtd">ruleml-datalog.dtd</a>'s
query-extended rulebase definition is inherited by
<a href="http://www.ruleml.org/dtd/0.8/ruleml-hornlog.dtd">ruleml-hornlog.dtd</a>,
where queries in datalog use only inds and vars but queries in hornlog automatically also permit cterms
(because hornlog atoms permit cterms).
</p>
<p>
RuleML queries are illustrated by our business-rule example
<a href="http://www.ruleml.org/exa/0.8/discount.ruleml">discount.ruleml</a>
(<a href="http://www.ruleml.org/exa/0.8/discount.ruleml.txt">discount.ruleml.txt</a>)
and by
<a href="http://www.w3.org/People/Eric/">Eric Prud'hommeaux</a>'s
<a href="http://www.w3.org/2001/11/13-RDF-Query-Rules/">RDF Query example</a>
<a href="http://www.ruleml.org/exa/0.8/wsdl-rdf-query.ruleml">wsdl-rdf-query.ruleml</a>
(<a href="http://www.ruleml.org/exa/0.8/wsdl-rdf-query.ruleml.txt">wsdl-rdf-query.ruleml.txt</a>).
</p>
<p>
This query incorporation into RuleML assumes that the sublanguage expressiveness
should be the same for 'assertions' (facts and imps) and for the 'requests' (queries) on them.
So, it cannot, e.g., express queries on ground triples
(containing no variables) via non-ground triples (containing variables):
<a href="http://www.ruleml.org/exa/0.8/creator.ruleml">creator.ruleml</a>
(<a href="http://www.ruleml.org/exa/0.8/creator.ruleml.txt">creator.ruleml.txt</a>).
However, users can still employ one rulebase (module) with its DTD for 'assertions',
and another rulebase (module) with a different DTD for 'requests'.
</p>
</section>


<section label="OO">
<header>Object-Oriented RuleML</header>

<p>
Via <a href="indoo">Object-Oriented RuleML (OO RuleML)</a> frame-like knowledge representation
with facts (instances) and rules (methods) is now directly supported.
</p>
</section>


<section label="ASP">
<header>ASP RuleML (Updated: 2006-04-06)</header>

<p>
<a href="http://www.kr.tuwien.ac.at/staff/roman/ruleml/">ASP RuleML</a> defines a sublanguage of RuleML for answer-set programs in
XML Schema. This variant facilitates the specification of a number of
ASP-related constructs in a general manner. Moreover, it constitutes a
base language for specific ASP extensions, such as HEX-programs.
</p>
</section>


<section label="RIF">
<header>RIF  (Initiated: 2010-08-14)</header>
<p>
RIF RuleML specifications are being collected here:
<itemize>
<item>
  <a href="http://ruleml.org/rif/RIF-CASPD.html">RIF-CASPD</a>
</item>
<item>
  <a href="http://ruleml.org/rif/RIF-CLPWD.html">RIF-CLPWD</a>
</item>
</itemize>
</p>
</section>


<section>
<header>RDF</header>

<p>
An experimental RDF translator for a subset of RuleML 0.7 is available in XSLT:
<a href="http://www.ruleml.org/inrdf.html">RuleML in RDF Version 0.2</a>.
RuleML 0.8 now stands in the direct <a href="http://www.ruleml.org/0.8/#Context">Context</a>
of RDF.
</p>
<p>
2001-06-20: <a href="http://www.dfki.uni-kl.de/~sintek/">Michael Sintek</a> has implemented
a (Java) parser for an RDF version of the Horn-logic subset of RuleML 0.8;
it reflects an RDF RuleML syntax
by (Java) classes that currently generate textual Horn clauses but could be adapted for generating
the XML RuleML syntax:
<a href="http://www.dfki.uni-kl.de/frodo/rdf2java/">The FRODO rdf2java Tool</a>.
A converse translator from XML RuleML 0.8 to RDF RuleML 0.8 should be easier to write in XSLT
than was possible for the above-linked RuleML 0.7 translator.
</p>
</section>


<section label="Lite">
<header>RuleML Lite</header>

<p>
<a href="http://www.daml.org/listarchive/joint-committee/1490.html">RuleML Lite</a> has been developed basically
as a RuleML subset compatible with RDF and OWL-DL that covers webized unary and binary Datalog facts, rules, and queries.
The RuleML Lite design has interacted with the <a href="http://www.daml.org/2003/11/swrl/">SWRL</a> design via
the <a href="http://www.daml.org/committee/">Joint Committee</a>.
</p>
</section>


<section label="FOL">
<header>FOL RuleML</header>

<p>
The <a href="http://www.ruleml.org/fol/">FOL RuleML</a> language has been developed in interaction between
the <a href="#Structure">RuleML Steering Committee</a> and the <a href="http://www.daml.org/committee/">Joint Committee</a>,
with input from <a href="http://philebus.tamu.edu/mailman/listinfo/scl">Simplified Common Logic (SCL)</a>.
FOL RuleML shares/reuses most of the earlier RuleML LP syntax,
incorporating First-Order-Logic quantifiers and disjunctions as well as equivalence and negation.
FOL RuleML strives for a strict separation of declarative content from procedural (Assert, Query) performatives,
as pioneered by KQML.
This and further changes to the current <a href="http://www.ruleml.org/0.87/">RuleML 0.87</a>
will also benefit other sublanguages towards RuleML 0.9, in particular the Horn logic subset.
FOL RuleML is the rule component of <a href="http://www.daml.org/2004/11/fol/">SWRL FOL</a>
and a proposed FOL content language for <a href="http://www.swsi.org/">SWSI</a>.
It can be viewed as a generalization of SWRL FOL
in that it is an XML form of full FOL, with n-ary relations (predicate symbols) and
constructors (logical function symbols).
</p>
<p>
2004-11-02: <a href="http://www.ruleml.org/fol/">FOL RuleML 0.9</a> has been released,
using a <a href="http://www.ruleml.org/fol/#SynSem">monolithic DTD specification</a>.
</p>
<p>
2004-11-14: An <a href="http://lists.w3.org/Archives/Public/www-rdf-rules/2004Nov/0008.html">FOL RuleML announcement</a> has been sent.
</p>
</section>


<section label="Induction">
<header>Induction</header>

<p>
The FLIP Group uses RuleML in machine learning:
<a href="http://www.dsic.upv.es/~flip/RuleML/">About using RuleML for expressing machine learning knowledge</a>.
In the <a href="http://lispminer.vse.cz">LispMiner</a> project
work with RuleML is directed towards statistical association rules.
</p>
</section>


<section label="Translators">
<header>Translators</header>

<p>
Since RuleML should help rule-system interoperation,
(XSLT, ...) translators for RuleML rulebases are rather important. Please send us further translator
pairs between your system and RuleML -- even if your translators are (still)
partial.
</p>
<p>
In February 2001 <a href="http://www.daml.org/people/mdean/">Mike Dean</a> created the first operational RuleML rulebase,
<a href="http://www.daml.org/2001/02/gedcom-ruleml/">GEDCOM</a>,
with rules on family relationships (child, spouse, etc.) run via XSLT translators to the XSB, JESS, and n3/cwm engines.
</p>
<p>
2001-09-17: <a href="http://www.cs.unb.ca/~boley/">Harold Boley</a>
has specified <a href="http://www.relfun.org/ruleml/rfml-ruleml.html">XSLT translators between the Horn-logic subsets of RuleML and RFML</a>.
These can make implementations of both systems available to each other and
permit, e.g., a preliminary HTML rendering of RuleML rulebases.
The XSLT stylesheets may also serve as blueprints for specifying further translators
to/fro RuleML.
</p>
<p>
2001-09-19: <a href="http://www.aifb.uni-karlsruhe.de/WBS/aeb/">Andreas Eberhart</a>
implemented an alpha version of <a href="http://www.i-u.de/schools/eberhart/ontojava/">OntoJava</a>.
The basic idea is to automatically map Protégé ontologies, instances defined
in them, and RuleML rules into a sinlge Java main memory DB / rule engine
that can then be used as the basis of an application.
He is looking forward to hearing of your ideas and input.
</p>
<p>
2002-02-04: <a href="http://www.aifb.uni-karlsruhe.de/WBS/aeb/">Andreas Eberhart</a>
extended <a href="http://www.i-u.de/schools/eberhart/ontojava/">OntoJava</a>
by reaction rules:
<code><![CDATA[
<java>
        runtime.Loader.load("http://localhost:8080/servlet/SearchGate?flight="
                         + <var>F</var>.name, false);
</java>]]></code>
This example loads RDF info into the DB, which comes from a kind of Web Service.
So emails can be sent as well, etc.
While this is not 'cross-platform', it should be interessting from an engineering
point of view.
</p>
<p>
2002-07-08: <a href="mailto:stabet@ruleml.org">Said Tabet</a> created an
<a href="http://www.ruleml.org/jess/RuleMLTransform.xsl">XSLT stylesheet</a>
for transforming from a version of RuleML to Jess.
The full Java environment for running this is available from
<a href="mailto:stabet@ruleml.org">Said Tabet</a>.
</p>
<p>
2003-08-26: Stephen Greene has specified
<a href="http://www.ruleml.org/ooruleml-xslt/oo2prml.html">XSLT translators between Positional and Object-Oriented RuleML</a>.</p>
<p>
2004-08-12: David Hirtle has created an
<a href="http://www.ruleml.org/0.87/#XSLT">XSLT translator between RuleML 0.86 and 0.87</a> as part of the
0.87 release.</p>
<p>
2005-03-01: David Hirtle has created an
<a href="http://www.ruleml.org/0.88/#XSLT-Based%20Upgrader">XSLT "upgrader"</a> to translate between RuleML 0.87 and 0.88 as part of the
0.88 release.  An <a href="http://www.ruleml.org/0.88/#XSLT-Based%20Normalizer">XSLT "normalizer"</a> for reconstructing all skipped role tags to achieve a fully-expanded, normal form is also included with this release.</p>
<p>
2005-05-27: The
<a href="http://www.ruleml.org/0.89/#XSLT-Based%20Upgrader">XSLT "upgrader" from 0.88 to 0.89</a> has been created as part of the
0.89 release.  An <a href="http://www.ruleml.org/0.89/#XSLT-Based%20Normalizer">updated XSLT "normalizer"</a> for achieving a normal form is also included.</p>
<p>2005-09-13: Jie Li has updated an earlier translator from RFML to RuleML <a href="http://www.ruleml.org/usecases/chemxelem/#XSLT%20Stylesheet">as part of the ChemXelem use case</a>.</p>

</section>


<section label="Engines">
<header>Engines (Updated: 2008-06-30)</header>

<p>
One or more rule engines will be needed for executing RuleML rulebases.
On 2000-11-15, the RuleML Initiative thus joined forces with the
Java Specification Request <a href="http://java.sun.com/aboutJava/communityprocess/jsr/jsr_094_ruleengine.html">JSR-000094 Java Rule Engine API</a>.
This cooperation will enable a direct cross-fertilization between the
complementary specifications of the open XML-based Rule Markup Language
and of the Java runtime API for rule engines.
</p>

<p>
2001-06-04: <a href="mailto:jens.dietrich@unforgettable.com">Jens Dietrich</a>
implemented the first complete input-processing-output environment for RuleML.
To download the api (source code) click
<a href="http://www.mandarax.org/downloads.html">Mandarax RuleML</a>.
Any feedback is welcome! If you have problems, don't hesitate to contact Jens
for assistance.
</p>
<p>
2002-03-08: <a href="mailto:jens.dietrich@unforgettable.com">Jens Dietrich</a>
has finally published <a href="http://www.mandarax.org/downloads.html">Mandarax 1.6</a>
with major improvements, including new docs and all the features discussed in the
<a href="http://www.mandarax.org/docs/dagstuhl.pdf">Mandarax Dagstuhl Talk</a>.
One of the new packages is
<a href="http://www.mandarax.org/downloads/xkb_b1.jar">xkb_b1.jar</a>
-- it contains
a modular driver to translate rule bases to XML and vice versa. I.e., there
are tiny
adapter objects responsible for exporting/importing rules, facts, terms
etc.
This should enable us to set up a reference application for any new standard
in hours.
</p>

<p>
2001-06-26: <a href="http://www.dfki.uni-kl.de/~sintek/">Michael Sintek</a>
has implemented a small XSB-based engine that can also be looked at as
the first RuleML querying <i>agent</i>.
It's a servlet (running in Tomcat) that receives RuleML rulebases in
RDF RuleML syntax (since he uses <a href="http://www.dfki.uni-kl.de/frodo/rdf2java/">The FRODO rdf2java Tool</a>)
together with some queries, evaluates them with XSB Prolog (in auto-tabling mode,
which should be equivalent to bottom-up evaluation!), and returns the result
as an HTML page containing the bindings as facts of instantiated queries.
A future version must, of course,
return a RuleML file.
Simply try
<a href="http://serv-4100.dfki.uni-kl.de:8765/ruleml/">this URL</a>.
Click on 'example' and paste the RDF RuleML popping up into the input window (note
that pasting XML/RDF cannot be directly done in IE, only in Netscape; use
"view source" in IE).
Alternatively, you can use the
<a href="http://serv-4100.dfki.uni-kl.de:8765/ruleml/rulemltrans.html">Prolog parser and RDF translator</a>
to generate the RDF RuleML.
Since we cannot guarantee that the above URLs always work (server reboots etc.),
<a href="xsb-rdf-ruleml.gif">this picture</a> shows the agent in action.
Any feedback is welcome! If you have problems, don't hesitate to contact Michael
for assistance.
</p>

<p>
2002-02-06: <a href="http://www.cs.unb.ca/~bspencer">Bruce Spencer</a> further refined
<a href="http://www.cs.unb.ca/~bspencer/dagstuhl-jdrew.pdf">The Design of j-DREW, a Deductive Reasoning Engine for the Semantic Web</a>.
</p>
<p>
2005-05-06: Marcel Ball [maball AT gmail DOT com] revised the documentation of
<a href="http://www.jdrew.org/oojdrew/">OO jDREW</a>, summarized in the Position Paper
<a href="http://www.ruleml.org/w3c-ws-rules/implementing-ruleml-w3c-ws.html">Implementing RuleML Using Schemas, Translators, and Bidirectional Interpreters</a>
of the
<a href="http://www.w3.org/2004/12/rules-ws/cfp">W3C Workshop on Rule Languages for Interoperability</a>.
</p>
<p>
2007-07-26: Benjamin Craig [ben.craig AT unb DOT ca] has been continuing the development of
<a href="http://www.jdrew.org/oojdrew/">OO jDREW</a> with a series of extended releases,
and is developing the OO jDREW part of <a href="http://responder.ruleml.org/">Rule Responder</a>.
</p>
<p>2008-06-30: A team led by <a 
href="http://lpis.csd.auth.gr/people/nbassili/">Nick Bassiliades</a>,  <a
href="http://www.ics.forth.gr/%7Eantoniou/">Grigoris Antoniou</a> and <a
href="http://www.governatori.net/">Guido Governatori</a> has released a 
new version of <a
href="http://lpis.csd.auth.gr/systems/dr-device.html#v081">DR-Device 
(version 0.81)</a> with support
for modalities and proof exporting. DR-Device is a defeasible logic 
reasoning system with priorities among
rules, two types of negation (strong, default) and conflicting (mutually 
exclusive) literals.
The system is implemented on top of CLIPS and has been extended to 
introduce rule modes that determine
the modality of the conclusion and modalized literals in the premises of 
rule bodies.
Furthermore, the system exports in a formal RuleML-like representation 
an explanation for the proof of the rule program conclusions.
The aim is (a) to take advantage of the expressive power of modal logics 
to define various agent behaviors, and (b) to
to increase user/agent trust towards rule-based Semantic Web 
applications.</p>
</section>


<section label="POSL">
<header>Positional-Slotted Language</header>

<p>
The Positional-Slotted presentation, shorthand, and exchange syntax for rules
(<a href="http://www.ruleml.org/submission/ruleml-shortation.html">POSL</a>)
merges Prolog's positional and F-Logic's slotted syntaxes.
Its need has emerged from discussions on ASCII syntaxes in the <a href="http://www.daml.org/committee/">Joint Committee</a>.
</p>
</section>


<section label="Interfaces">
<header>User Interfaces (Updated: 2011-03-21)</header>

<p>
RuleML Participant Jens Dietrich's Oryx (version 2.1) has a graphical Knowledge Editor for business rules and a Repository that
contains the description of predicates, functions, and database connections.
"Oryx works with open XML based formats, support for the emerging RuleML standard and the open source Mandarax XKB 1.0 format is
included."  (<a href="http://www.jbdietrich.com/">http://www.jbdietrich.com</a>).
</p>
<p>
<a href="http://www.dfki.uni-kl.de/~sintek/">Michael Sintek</a>
has implemented a
<a href="http://serv-4100.dfki.uni-kl.de:8765/ruleml/rulemltrans.html">Prolog parser and RDF translator</a>
to generate RDF RuleML.
</p>
<p>
<a href="http://www.aifb.uni-karlsruhe.de/WBS/aeb/">Andreas Eberhart</a> wrote
a small tool that allows you to convert Prolog (currently, Datalog) rules to RuleML.
This <a href="http://www.i-u.de/schools/eberhart/prolog2ruleml/">Prolog2RuleML</a> tool
is available both online and as a command line version.
</p>
<p>
2005-12-13: A team led by <a href="http://www.csd.auth.gr/~nbassili">Nick Bassiliades</a>
and <a href="http://www.ics.forth.gr/~antoniou/">Grigoris Antoniou</a>
has released <a href="http://iskp.csd.auth.gr/systems/dr-device.html">VDR-Device (version 0.27)</a>.
VDR-Device is a visual environment for developing defeasible logic rule 
bases for the Semantic Web.
VDR-Device integrates a graphical RuleML-compliant rule editor and a 
defeasible reasoning system that
processes RDF data and RDF Schema ontologies. The rule editor constrains 
the allowed vocabulary
after analyzing the input RDF Schema ontologies, preventing potential 
syntactic and semantic errors.
The reasoning system supports all defeasible logic rule types, 
priorities among rules, two types of negation
and conflicting literals.
</p>
<p>
2006-04-28: A Java Web Start application called <a href="http://www.ruleml.org/translator">TRANSLATOR</a> has been developed by David Hirtle for translating from <a href="http://www.ifi.unizh.ch/attempto/">Attempto Controlled English</a> to RuleML.
The reverse direction, RuleML to English, is a planned extension.
</p>
<p>
2009-12-08: S2REd is a syntactic+semantic text-based RuleML editor.
It is a full-fledged textual XML editor that features: syntax 
highlighting, spell checking, brace matching, code-block coloring, 
pretty-printing, well-formedness and validation checking.
Nevertheless, S2REd is more than an XML editor: its a tool totally 
dedicated to RuleML authoring, offering domain-specific semantically 
enabled functionality.
Developed by Thetida Zetta, Efstratios Kontopoulos, and Nick Bassiliades.
Project URL: <a href="https://sourceforge.net/projects/s2red/">S2REd</a>
</p>
<p>
2011-03-21: <a href="https://sourceforge.net/projects/s2red/">S2REd</a>, 
the syntactic+semantic RuleML editor developed by Thetida Zetta, 
Efstratios Kontopoulos, and Nick Bassiliades at <a 
href="http://lpis.csd.auth.gr">Aristotle University of Thessaloniki</a>, Greece,
has been upgraded to provide support for RuleML 1.0.
</p>

</section>


<section label="Library">
<header>Rulebase Library (Updated: 2010-12-28)</header>

<p>
A library of RuleML rulebases is being accumulated here as a collection of use cases
for further design discussion and as examples for practical rule exchange
(<a href="http://www.ruleml.org/lib">RuleML Library</a>).
The highest version of RuleML (currently 0.86) should be used whenever possible.
If you have an entry, please send us its pointer.
The discounting business rules example introduces some of the features:
<a href="exa/0.8/discount.ruleml">discount.ruleml</a>
(<a href="exa/0.8/discount.ruleml.txt">discount.ruleml.txt</a>).
<itemize>
  <item>
2002-03-06: <a href="http://www.daml.org/people/mdean/">Mike Dean</a>'s
<a href="http://www.daml.org/2001/02/gedcom-ruleml/">GEDCOM</a> rulebase
<a href="http://www.daml.org/2001/02/gedcom-ruleml/gedcom-relations.xml">GEDCOM RuleML 0.7</a>,
with rules on family relationships (child, spouse, etc.), has been made available:
<a href="http://www.ruleml.org/lib/gedcom/gedcom-relations0.8.ruleml">GEDCOM RuleML 0.8</a> (View | Page Source).
<br/>
This is Elina Hotman's result of having
<a href="http://www.daml.org/2001/02/gedcom-ruleml/gedcom-relations.xml">GEDCOM RuleML 0.7</a>
(local copy: <a href="http://www.ruleml.org/lib/gedcom/gedcom-relations0.7.xml">GEDCOM RuleML 0.7</a>),
first transformed by the XSLT stylesheet
<a href="http://www.ruleml.org/lib/gedcom/ruleml2rfml_gedcom.xsl">ruleml2rfml_gedcom.xsl</a>
(a <a href="http://www.relfun.org/ruleml/rfml-ruleml.html">translator</a> version of
<a href="http://www.relfun.org/ruleml/ruleml2rfml.xsl">ruleml2rfml.xsl</a>)
to the -- likewise positional -- <a href="http://www.relfun.org/rfml/">RFML</a> form
<a href="http://www.ruleml.org/lib/gedcom/gedcom-relations0.8.rfml">GEDCOM RFML 0.8</a>,
and then having that further transformed by the XSLT stylesheet
<a href="http://www.ruleml.org/lib/gedcom/rfml2ruleml_gedcom.xsl">rfml2ruleml_gedcom.xsl</a>
(a <a href="http://www.relfun.org/ruleml/rfml-ruleml.html">translator</a> version of
<a href="http://www.relfun.org/ruleml/rfml2ruleml.xsl">rfml2ruleml.xsl</a>)
to the -- role-using --  RuleML 0.8 form
<a href="http://www.ruleml.org/lib/gedcom/gedcom-relations0.8.ruleml">GEDCOM RuleML 0.8</a>.
<br/>
Coincidentally, <a href="http://www.agfa.com/w3c/jdroo/">Jos De Roo</a> used
<a href="http://www.daml.org/2001/02/gedcom-ruleml/gedcom-relations.xml">GEDCOM RuleML 0.7</a> to generate
<a href="http://www.agfa.com/w3c/euler/gedcom-relations.n3">GEDCOM N3</a>, from which
<a href="mailto:jonathan@openhealth.org">Jonathan Borden</a> generated
<a href="http://www.openhealth.org/RDF/gedcom-relations-xt.xml">GEDCOM RDFxt</a>
(<a href="http://lists.w3.org/Archives/Public/www-webont-wg/2002Mar/0085.html">www-webont-wg -- LANG: GEDCOM N3 as RDFxt</a>).
Thus, <a href="http://www.daml.org/2001/02/gedcom-ruleml/">GEDCOM</a> looks like
a good benchmark for transforming between RuleML and related systems
(future transformers should directly start off from
<a href="http://www.ruleml.org/lib/gedcom/gedcom-relations0.8.ruleml">GEDCOM RuleML 0.8</a>
or higher).
A draft specification for the original <a href="http://www.familysearch.org/GEDCOM/GedXML60.pdf">GEDCOM XML</a>
is available.
  </item>
  <item>
2002-06-24: <a href="mailto:sabrina.scherer@dfki.de?subject=RACSA">Sabrina Scherer</a> and <a href="mailto:benjamin.olschok@dfki.de?subject=RACSA">Benjamin Olschok</a>, University of Saarbrücken,
in cooperation with <a href="http://www.cs.unb.ca/~boley/">Harold Boley</a>, DFKI,
have completed the prototype of a
Rule-Applying Comparison-Shopping Agent, <a href="http://www.dfki.de/racsa">RACSA</a>,
which takes into account
various (discount-like) rules for computing the special price
a customer will be offered.
RACSA is based on RuleML, Mandarax, and Java;
it is currently being developed for comparing refrigerator end prices in
the German and European market, but can be easily adapted to other products and/or markets.
A RACSA servlet and the comparison-shopping rulebases will soon be made
available <a href="http://www.dfki.de/racsa">here</a> for testing.
  </item>
  <item>
2002-07-08: <a href="mailto:stabet@ruleml.org">Said Tabet</a> created an
<a href="http://www.ruleml.org/jess/RuleMLTransform.xsl">XSLT stylesheet</a>
for transforming from a version of RuleML to Jess.
This is exemplified by an animal rulebase transformed from its neutral
<a href="http://www.ruleml.org/jess/rules1.xml">RuleML version</a>
(<a href="http://www.ruleml.org/jess/rules1.xml.txt">rules1.xml.txt</a>)
into a forward-reasoning
<a href="http://www.ruleml.org/jess/rules1.clp">Jess version</a>.
The full Java environment for running this is available from
<a href="mailto:stabet@ruleml.org">Said Tabet</a>.
  </item>
  <item>
2004-02-27: The New Brunswick Business Knowledge Base, <a href="http://www.ruleml.org/usecases/nbbizkb/">NBBizKB</a>,
was created as a major use case for <a href="indoo">OO RuleML</a>.
  </item>
  <item>
2004-05-15: Based on the RuleML and <a href="http://savannah.nongnu.org/projects/cofi/">Cofi</a> projects,
the Rule-Applying Collaborative Filtering System (<a href="http://www.ondelette.com/lemire/abstracts/COLA2003.html">RACOFI</a>) has
meanwhile led to a portal for publishing, searching, and rating independent music in MP3 (<a href="http://www.indiscover.net/">inDiscover</a>).
  </item>
  <item>
2005-09-13: The <a href="http://www.ruleml.org/usecases/chemxelem/">ChemXelem</a> use case consists of a RuleML knowledge base about the Periodic System of the Elements generated from a non-XML source.
  </item>
  <item>
2008-07-31: RuleML/XML and RuleML/POSL rulebases have been built for Expert Finding (<a href="http://www.ruleml.org/usecases/foaf/findxprt/">FindXpRT</a>),
  eTourism (<a href="http://ruleml.org/usecases/etourplan/">eTourPlan</a>),
  Health Information Retrieval (<a href="http://gge.athost.net/">http://gge.athost.net</a>), and
  Personal Agents (<a href="http://responder.ruleml.org/">Rule Responder</a>).
  </item>
  <item>
2010-12-28: The well-known Wine Ontology is made available as a sizeable RuleML Use Case in Web rule conversion, upgrading, and normalization (<a href="http://ruleml.org/usecases/wineonto/">WineOnto</a>)
  </item>
</itemize>
</p>
</section>

<section label="Papers-Publications">
<header>Papers-Publications (Updated: 2010-02-07)</header>
<p>
Check out some <a href="http://scholar.google.com/scholar?q=RuleML">Google Scholar results for RuleML</a>.
</p>
<itemize>
  <item>David Hirtle, <a href="http://www.ruleml.org/translator/TRANSLATOR-CaSTA.pdf">TRANSLATOR: A TRANSlator from LAnguage TO Rules</a>, Canadian Symposium on Text Analysis (CaSTA), Fredericton, October 2006.
  </item>
  <item>
Marcel Ball, Harold Boley, David Hirtle, Jing Mei, Bruce Spencer: <a href="http://www.ruleml.org/w3c-ws-rules/implementing-ruleml-w3c-ws.html">Implementing RuleML Using Schemas, Translators, and Bidirectional Interpreters</a>, <a href="http://www.w3.org/2004/12/rules-ws/">W3C Workshop on Rule Languages for Interoperability</a>, April 2005, Washington, D.C.
  </item> 
  <item>
Yevgen Biletskiy, Harold Boley, David Hirtle: <a href="http://www.ece.unb.ca/biletskiy/RuleML-LO-Ontologies.pdf">Building RuleML Learning Object Ontologies on the Semantic Web</a>.
Submitted for review, September 2005.
  </item>
  <item>
Yevgen Biletskiy, Harold Boley, Luqian Zhu: <a href="http://www.ece.unb.ca/biletskiy/RuleML-Inteoperation.pdf">A RuleML-Based Ontology for Interoperation between Learning Objects and Learners</a>, UCFV Research Review, 
to appear 2005.
  </item>
  <item>
Harold Boley: <a href="http://www.dfki.uni-kl.de/~boley/xmlrdf.html">A Web Data Model Unifying XML and RDF</a>. Draft, September 2001.
  </item>
  <item>
Harold Boley: <a href="http://www.dfki.uni-kl.de/~boley/ruleml-mht.pdf">The Rule Markup Language: RDF-XML Data Model, XML Schema Hierarchy, and
XSL Transformations</a>, Invited Talk, INAP2001, Tokyo, October 2001.
  </item>
  <item>
Harold Boley, Said Tabet, and Gerd Wagner: <a href="http://www.semanticweb.org/SWWS/program/full/paper20.pdf">Design Rationale of RuleML: A Markup
Language for Semantic Web Rules</a>, Proc. SWWS'01, Stanford, July/August 2001.
  </item>
  <item>
Andreas Eberhart, <a href="http://www.cs.unb.ca/ai2002/baseweb/BASeWEB2002_Paper1.pdf">An Agent Infrastructure based on Semantic Web Standards</a>,
Workshop on Business Agents and the Semantic Web at the AI 2002,
Calgary, Canada
  </item>
  <item>
Andreas Eberhart, <a href="http://link.springer.de/link/service/series/0558/papers/2342/23420102.pdf">Automatic Generation of Java/SQL based Inference Engines
from RDF Schema and RuleML</a>, International Semantic Web Conference
2002, Sardinia
  </item>
  <item>
Andreas Eberhart, <a href="http://www.i-u.de/schools/eberhart/wsdf">Towards Universal Web Service Clients</a>, <a href="http://www.w3c.rl.ac.uk/Euroweb/">EuroWeb 2002 Conference</a>, St Anne's College Oxford, UK, December 17 and 18th 2002.
  </item>
  <item>
Benjamin Grosof: <a href="http://ebusiness.mit.edu/bgrosof/paps/wits01-extended-working-paper-12-01.pdf">Representing E-Business Rules for the Semantic Web: Situated Courteous Logic Programs in RuleML</a>,
Proc. Workshop on Information Technologies and Systems (WITS '01), New Orleans, December, 2001.
  </item>
  <item>
Benjamin Grosof, Mahesh D. Gandhe, and Timothy W. Finin: <a href="http://www.soi.city.ac.uk/~msch/conf/ruleml/grosof.pdf">SweetJess: Translating DamlRuleML to Jess</a>,
Proc. International Workshop on Rule Markup Languages for Business Rules on the Semantic Web,
Sardinia (Italy), June 2002.
  </item>
  <item>
Benjamin Grosof and Terrence Poon: <a href="http://www.soi.city.ac.uk/~msch/conf/ruleml/grosof2.pdf">Representing Agent Contracts with Exceptions using XML Rules, Ontologies, and Process Descriptions</a>,
Proc. International Workshop on Rule Markup Languages for Business Rules on the Semantic Web,
Sardinia (Italy), June 2002.
  </item>
  <item>
Jae Kyu Lee and Mye M. Sohn: <a href="http://portal.acm.org/citation.cfm?doid=769800.769802">The eXtensible Rule Markup Language</a>, Communications of the ACM, Volume 46, Issue 5, pp. 59-64, May 2003.
  </item>
  <item>
Steve Ross-Talbot, Harold Boley, and Said Tabet:
<a href="http://www.appdevadvisor.co.uk/Downloads/ADA6_5/ross6_5.pdf">Playing by the Rules</a>,
<a href="http://www.appdevadvisor.co.uk/">Application Development Advisor</a> 6(5), June 2002, 38-43.
  </item>
  <item>
Michael Schroeder and Gerd Wagner (Eds.): <a href="http://CEUR-WS.org/Vol-60/">Proceedings of the International
Workshop on  Rule Markup Languages for Business Rules on the Semantic Web</a>.
Sardinia, Italy, June 14, 2002. CEUR-WS Publication Vol-60.
  </item>
  <item>
Gerd Wagner: <a href="http://tmitwww.tm.tue.nl/staff/gwagner/myruleml/GRML.pdf">How to Design a General Rule Markup Language?</a>,  Invited Talk, Workshop XML Technologien für das Semantic Web (XSW 2002), Berlin, June 2002.
  </item>
  <item>
Gerd Wagner, Said Tabet, and Harold Boley: <a href="http://www.omg.org/docs/br/03-10-02.pdf">MOF-RuleML: The Abstract Syntax of RuleML as a MOF Model</a>,
<a href="http://www.integrate2003.com">Integrate 2003</a>, OMG Meting, October 2003, Boston.
  </item>
</itemize>
</section>

<section label="Structure">
<header>Structure (Updated: 2008-06-30)</header>
<itemize>
  <item>
<b>RuleML, Co-Chairs:</b> <a href="http://www.cs.unb.ca/~boley/">Harold Boley</a> &amp; <a href="http://home.comcast.net/~stabet/">Said Tabet</a>
  </item>
   <item>
<b>Steering Committee:</b>  <a href="http://www.ee.unb.ca/biletskiy/">Yevgen Biletskiy</a>,
<a href="http://www.cs.unb.ca/~boley/">Harold Boley</a>,
<a href="http://www.daml.org/people/mdean/">Mike Dean</a>,
<a href="http://ebusiness.mit.edu/bgrosof/">Benjamin Grosof</a>,
<a href="http://www.cs.sunysb.edu/~kifer">Michael Kifer</a>,
<a href="http://www.soi.city.ac.uk/~firmata/">Alex Kozlenkov</a>,
<a href="http://dl-web.man.ac.uk/~panz/Zhilin/">Jeff Z. Pan</a>,
<a href="http://ibis.in.tum.de/staff/paschke/index.htm">Adrian Paschke</a>,
<a href="http://www.cs.unb.ca/~bspencer">Bruce Spencer</a>,
<a href="mailto:gstam@softlab.ece.ntua.gr">Giorgos Stamou</a>,
<a href="mailto:SUZETTE@mitre.org">Suzette Stoutenburg</a>,
<a href="http://home.comcast.net/~stabet/">Said Tabet</a>,
<a href="http://tmitwww.tm.tue.nl/staff/gwagner/">Gerd Wagner</a>
  </item>
  <item>
<b>Advisory Board:</b> <a href="http://www.research.ibm.com/people/a/adi/">Asaf Adi</a>, <a href="http://www.aifb.uni-karlsruhe.de/WBS/aeb/">Andreas Eberhart</a>, <a href="mailto:steve@pi4tech.com">Steve Ross-Talbot</a>
  </item>
  <item>
<b>Reaction Rules (<a href="http://ibis.in.tum.de/research/ReactionRuleML/">Reaction RuleML</a>) Technical Group, Co-Chairs:</b> <a href="http://ibis.in.tum.de/staff/paschke/index.htm">Adrian Paschke</a> &amp; <a href="alex.kozlenkov@betfair.com">Alex Kozlenkov</a>,
Mailing list: <a href="http://mail.ruleml.org/pipermail/reaction-tg/">reaction-tg</a>
  </item>
  <item>
<b>Ontology Combination Technical Group, Co-Chairs:</b> <a href="http://ebusiness.mit.edu/bgrosof/">Benjamin Grosof</a> &amp; <a href="http://www.aifb.uni-karlsruhe.de/WBS/aeb/">Andreas Eberhart</a>
  </item>
    
  <item>
<b>Defeasible Logic in RuleML (<a href="http://defeasible.org/RuleML/">Defeasible RuleML</a>) Technical Group, Co-Chairs:</b> <a href=" http://lpis.csd.auth.gr/people/nbassili/">Nick Bassiliades</a> &amp; <a href="http://www.governatori.net/">Guido Governatori</a>
  </item>

  <item>
<b>Frames, Objects, and RUle Markup (<!-- <a href="http://forum.semanticweb.org/">FORUM</a> --> <a href="http://forum.projects.semwebcentral.org/">FORUM</a>) Technical Group, Co-Chairs:</b> <a href="http://www.cs.sunysb.edu/~kifer">Michael Kifer</a> &amp; <a href="http://www.ontoprise.de/members/angele/publications.htm">Jürgen Angele</a>
  </item>
  <item>
<b>Fuzziness in RuleML (<a href="http://image.ntua.gr/FuzzyRuleML/">Fuzzy RuleML</a>) Technical Group, Co-Chairs:</b> <a href="mailto:gstam@softlab.ece.ntua.gr">Giorgos Stamou</a> &amp; <a href="http://dl-web.man.ac.uk/~panz/Zhilin/">Jeff Z. Pan</a>
  </item>
  <item>
<b>RuleML-Based Responder (<a href="http://responder.ruleml.org/">Rule Responder</a>) Technical Group, Co-Chairs:</b> <a href="http://ibis.in.tum.de/staff/paschke/index.htm">Adrian Paschke</a> &amp; <a href="http://www.cs.unb.ca/~boley/">Harold Boley</a>,
Mailing list: <a href="http://tech.groups.yahoo.com/group/Rule_Responder/">responder-tg</a>
  </item>
</itemize>
</section>

<section label="Contacts">
<header>Contacts</header>
<p>
If you are interested to join the RuleML Initiative,
please send a link describing your
work related to rule markup to <a href="http://www.cs.unb.ca/~boley/">Harold Boley</a>
and <a href="http://home.comcast.net/~stabet/">Said Tabet</a>;
same for general RuleML questions/suggestions.
Depending on your specific RuleML interests, you may also contact
some RuleML Technical Group (<a href="#Structure">select above</a>) or
some RuleML Participant (<a href="#Participants-Systems">select above</a>).
You are encouraged to subscribe to our main
mailing list: <a href="http://mail.ruleml.org/pipermail/ruleml-all/2003-November/000000.html">ruleml-all</a>.
</p>
</section>


  <closing>
<p>
Site Contact:
<a href="http://www.cs.unb.ca/~boley/">Harold Boley</a>.
Page Version: 2011-03-21

<br/><br/><br/>

      <a name="Practice-Preach"/><small>"Practice what you preach": XML source of this homepage at <a href="index.xml">index.xml</a> (<a href="index.xml.txt">index.xml.txt</a>);
      <br/>
      transformed to HTML via the adaptation of <a href="http://www.dfki.uni-kl.de/~sintek/">Michael Sintek</a>'s SliML <a href="http://www.w3.org/TR/xslt">XSLT</a> stylesheet at <a href="homepage.xsl">homepage.xsl</a> (View | Page Source)
      </small>
</p>
  </closing>
</homepage>
